טוב, Tov, today's דף daf is ק"ל, kuf lamed, 130, the beginning
of a new פרק. perek. Certainly the פרק perek we just finished
was, I would say, the most challenging one in חולין. Chullin. Well,
of course, putting aside all the anatomical issues from way back. Anyway,
we now look at the last three chapters which focus on still
about issues around animals, but now about the gifts from animals, beginning
with the shearing of the sheep and of the pieces of the
שחיטה shechita of cows and sheep. And then the last פרק perek
of sending away the mother bird. So it's a nice little break
and change from what we've been doing. We start, this is הזרוע
והלחיים והקיבה, Hazroa Vehalechayayim Veakeiva, the arm and the jaw, an area
and of the sort of the mouth, and the תורה Torah says
that when a person slaughters an animal or a cow or a
sheep, they give the gift of the arm and of the jaw
of it to the כהנים. Kohanim. It's worth mentioning that, can I
have that חומש Chumash for a second?
I'll just read you the פסוק. pasuk. It is worth mentioning that,
you know, if you think about it, right, the כהנים Kohanim did
not have land, so they basically lived off of the gifts that
they received. The classic gifts that we know of course are תרומה,
Terumah, מעשר Maaser went to the לויים, Levi'im, but תרומה, Terumah, grain.
Okay, so that's grain is fine, you know, and I mean rabbinically
we extended it to things like fruits and vegetables,
biblically probably not, it's just the grain and the wine and the
oil.
But you know, what about the meat? Where are they getting the
meat from? So I guess if you get enough grain you can
sell it and trade it in for meat. But the תורה Torah
actually, which is often ignored, or not ignored, often forgotten, is the
תורה Torah actually also gives them a gift of the meat. And
that's the פסוק pasuk that says in, let me just find it
here.
We're going to discuss where exactly הזרוע והלחיים והקיבה Hazroa Vehalechayayim Veakeiva
extend, like the parameters of that, what's considered a זרוע? zeroa? Yeah,
yeah, yeah.
לחיים? Lechayayim?
לחיים Lechayayim is the like the, I don't know. And the קיבה,
keiva, the קיבה keiva is certainly the stomach. Hold on. I
am having a hard time just finding this. All right, well so
much for that right now. Hold on, this is giving me the
wrong פסוק. pasuk. What? י"ח? Yud Chet? Yeah, where is it? Hold
on. Oh, it's ט"ו. Tet Vav. All right. All right, so anyway,
so it says, there we go.
I thought there we went. Should have had this ready for beforehand,
sorry about that. Okay, there, why am I not finding it? I'll
let Michael find it for me.
All right, anyway, Michael here find the פסוק pasuk for me.
Michael's going to find the פסוק pasuk for me. All right, anyway,
I don't know why I'm having a hard time locating the פסוק.
pasuk. Anyway, so that's what you would give, הזרוע והלחיים והקיבה, Hazroa
Vehalechayayim Veakeiva, the arm, the mouth, and the maw. It's actually, there's
a famous מדרש, Midrash, you know, why specifically those? That connect this
to, there's a קיבה keiva mentioned by a כהן Kohen as well,
which is פנחס, Pinchas, right? By פנחס Pinchas it says that he
speared, you know, the Midianite woman and זמרי, Zimri, you know, through
the אל הקבה, el hakuba, הקיבה, hakeiva, the stomach, and he used
his arm, his זרוע zeroa to do it. So actually there's a
classic מדרש Midrash that speaks about, you know, and he was a
כהן, Kohen, that sort of sees it as symbolic of that. Thank
you very much. I don't know why I wasn't finding it because
all the references were off. Thank you. It's in י"ח. Yud Chet.
Okay, it starts with לא יהיה לכהנים הלוים כל שבט לוי חלק
ונחלה עם ישראל אשי ה' ונחלתו יאכלון. Lo yihyeh lakohanim halevi'im kol
shevet levi chelek venachala im yisrael ishei hashem venachalato yocheilun. They don't
have a portion, they eat the fire offerings of God. So when
they're in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, we know that they get
the קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, but they're not always in the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, and you know, the way God set it up is
they were only there like two weeks out of a year. So
what are they surviving on the rest of the time? So immediately
the next פסוק pasuk says וזה יהיה משפט הכהנים מאת העם מאת
זבחי הזבח אם שור אם שה ונתן לכהן הזרוע והלחיים והקיבה. Vezeh
yihyeh mishpat hakohanim mei'eit ha'am mei'eit zovechei hazevach im shor im seh
venatan lakohen hazroa vehalechayayim vehakeiva.
Normal people who just slaughter animals, they get the arm, the jaw,
and the stomach, one of the stomachs. Then ראשית דגנך תירשך ויצהרך
וראשית גז צאנך תתן לו. Reishit degancha tiroshcha veyitzharecha vereishit geiz tzoncha
titein lo.
The first of the grain and of the wine and of the
oil and, which will be our next פרק, perek, the first of
the shearing of the sheep. Shearing of the sheep of course you
use for clothes. So by the time you're done with this, you
have your clothes, you've got your grain, and you've got your meat,
so you're pretty much the staples of what you need. But of
course it's interesting that we tend to forget those other two and
think just about the תרומה, Terumah, but the פסוקים pesukim here put
it here and they juxtapose it to the fact because they have
nothing else in which they are supporting themselves, they're dedicated to עבודת
הקודש avodat hakodesh so they don't have their own
inheritance, they really most כהנים Kohanim worked only a couple of weeks.
Right, and therefore they have to live on...
live for those few weeks.
Well, no,
no, because the other... well, the other part is that the תורה
Torah indeed indicates that the כוהנים kohanim's role is not just in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that the כוהנים kohanim's role is also
as teachers, right? You know, יורו משפטיך ליעקב. Yoru mishpatecha l'Yaakov. Okay,
that's true, that is true, but it's, you know, also culturally, it's
a question of legally do they have to, but culturally that was
expected, that that was what they were doing is that they were
there to serve the people's religious needs in and out of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Yeah, weren't they allowed to buy meat in the store?
They were what?
Weren't they allowed to buy meat in the store?
They could buy meat in the store, but the point is that
these basic things are provided for them.
So they can, you can sell...
Yeah, sure, of course, yes, definitely. You could sell those things. Those
were not holy. Okay, so let's take a look.
Yeah, since it's the שחיטה shechita of the קרבן, korban, maybe not...
Do we have to give this to the כוהנים? kohanim? Technically, yes.
No, wait, since we don't know who's a
real כהן, kohen, we just set it aside?
No, no, it's...
we'll talk about it. Okay. All right, so let's take a look.
הזרוע והלחיים והקיבה. Hazroa vehalechayayim vehakeiva.
So, all right, that was the introduction. So, the זרוע, zroa, לחיים,
lechayayim, and קיבה, keiva,
these parts of the animal, the arm and the cheekbone and you
would, the stomach. I said a minute ago what some of the
symbolism of that might be. We can talk about that later. נוהג
בארץ ובחוץ לארץ, Noheg ba'aretz uvachutz la'aretz, it applies whether in Israel
and outside of Israel. It's not... and בפני הבית ושלא בפני הבית,
Bifnei habayis veshelo bifnei habayis, whether there's a Temple or not a
Temple. So Michael asks, do we do it nowadays? So we will
talk about that, but there's no reason we shouldn't based on this
משנה. Mishnah.
And it's not קדוש, kadosh, it's not like תרומה, terumah, so... so
the... so
we will talk about how we handle that. בחולין אבל לא
במוקדשין, Bechullin aval lo bemukdashin, in non-sanctified animals but not by קרבנות.
korbanos. קרבנות, Korbanos, this is not a gift. שהיה בדין, Shehayah badin,
and now interestingly here the משנה Mishnah reflects on
this issue about... about why is it... why does it not apply
by קרבנות. korbanos. ומה אם החולין שאין חייבין בחזה ושוק, Umah im
hachullin she'ein chayavin bachazeh veshouk,
so we've dealt with a lot of similar types of דרשות drashos
in the גמרא, Gemara, but it's less common that this appears in
the משנה, Mishnah, but here it does, these types of, you know,
דרשות. drashos. And here's the question. Here's why I might have thought
that this gift applies to קרבנות. korbanos. By חולין, chullin, that you
don't give the חזה chazeh and the שוק, shouk, you don't give
the breast and the thigh like you do by a שלמים, shelamim,
and nevertheless you don't give that to the כוהנים, kohanim, and
nevertheless you give these gifts. קדשים שחייבין בחזה ושוק, Kodshim shechayavin bachazeh
veshouk, קרבנות korbanos that we already know you give one gift to
the כוהנים, kohanim, the breast and the thigh by a שלמים, shelamim,
and presumably we're talking about a שלמים shelamim because it would be
an irrelevant point if we're talking about a חטאת chatas and an
עולה, olah, because an עולה olah you burn and a חטאת chatas
the כוהנים kohanim eat the whole thing anyway. So the only question
of whether you give this gift of זרוע, לחיים, וקיבה zroa, lechayayim,
and keiva from the קרבנות korbanos is by שלמים. shelamim. So the
argument is, if you're already giving one gift, if you're already giving
the חזה chazeh and שוק, shouk, so clearly you're more obligated to
give gifts here, so you should give even this second gift. Of
course the obvious counter-argument is, you don't have to give a second
gift because you're giving this gift. But okay, this is the קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. So אינו דין שחייב במתנות, eino din shechayav bamatnos,
how much more so by a שלמים shelamim should you give these
gifts of the זרוע, לחיים, וקיבה? zroa, lechayayim, and keiva? תלמוד לומר,
Talmud lomar, ואתן אתם לאהרן הכהן ולבניו לחק עולם, Ve'asain osam l'Aharon
hakohen ulvanav l'chok olam,
this is a verse by the שלמים shelamim and by the חזה
chazeh and שוק, shouk,
I give them to Aaron and his כוהנים kohanim for an eternal
edict. So only them. אין לו אלא מה שנאמר בענין, Ein lo
ela mah she'ne'emar binyan, when you're dealing with the קרבנות, korbanos, it's
only אותם, osam, it's only the חזה chazeh and the שוק, shouk,
only the breast and the thigh, and it is not these other
things. That's all they get from a קרבן. korban. Okay, then fine,
that's the little דרשה. drashah. Now it goes on to another point
which actually is only tangentially related to our issue of זרוע, לחיים,
וקיבה. zroa, lechayayim, and keiva. And this part of the משנה Mishnah
is exactly quoted word for word in בכורות, Bechoros, which is... which
is the מסכת masechet coming up. Let's take a look. כל הקדשים
שקדמו מום קבוע להקדשן. Kol hakodshim shekadmu mum kavuah lehekdeshan.
Now we have said, let me sort of tell you what the
point of this part of the משנה Mishnah is going to be.
We have said that זרוע, לחיים, וקיבה zroa, lechayayim, and keiva do
not apply to קרבנות. korbanos. Also, and the reason this part of
the משנה Mishnah is quoted in בכורות Bechoros is that the מצוה
mitzvah of בכור bechor does not apply to a קרבן. korban. If
you had an animal that was a קרבן, korban, let's say it
was a... a שלמים, shelamim, okay, or...
and it was a female, and then it gave birth. Would the
animal it gave birth to be a בכור bechor if it was
its firstborn? And the answer is no. We'll even find out that
even if this was a קרבן korban and then it got a
מום mum and you redeemed it, and then it gave birth, since
it had that residual קדושה kedushah of being a קרבן, korban, the
animal that it gave birth from it does not have... is not
a בכור. bechor. בכור Bechor is only from an animal that was
not a קרבן, korban, has no residual קרבן קדושה. korban kedushah.
So any animal it gives birth to is just not... you know,
just no בכור bechor from this animal?
No בכור bechor from an animal that is or was a קרבן,
korban, okay, even if it was redeemed. Also, our משנה Mishnah just
taught that there's no gift of זרוע, לחיים, וקיבה, zroa, lechayayim, and
keiva, no gift of the, you know, the arm and whatever, from
an animal that was a קרבן, korban, and similarly even from an
animal that once was a קרבן. korban. So what this משנה Mishnah
is now going to do is now going to talk about different
ways in which an animal can be sanctified, under what circumstance is
it considered to have been in the קרבן korban category that would
remove it... from בכור bechor and remove it from the gift of
זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zroa lechayayim vekeiva, and under what circumstances was it
not in the קורבן korban category and would not be excluded from
בכור bechor and not be excluded from those gifts. That's why this
משנה mishnah appears word for word here and word for word in
בכורות bechorot because it's basically telling you when is something in the
קורבן korban category, not in the קורבן korban category to lead to
this exclusion, and there are a couple things it could be excluded
from. So let's take a look. כל הקדשים שקדם מום קבוע להקדשם,
kol hakodashim shekodam mum kavua lehekdesham, all sacrifices that before they were
sanctified, this animal had a מום קבוע, mum kavua, a fixed blemish,
a blemish that was not going away. If it was a blemish
that was going away, that would heal, then it's not really considered
a מום. mum. But if it was a blemish that was not
going to heal and then you sanctified it, so this is important,
the moment you sanctified it, it was already determined that this animal
could not be a קורבן, korban, right? Because it had a מום
קבוע, mum kavua, wasn't going away, could not be a קורבן. korban.
If that's what you did, then you've never given it the sanctity
of a קורבן, korban, even if you took this beautiful looking cow
and you said הרי זו עולה harei zo olah or הרי זו
שלמים harei zo shelamim and you tried to make it a קורבן,
korban, if it had a מום קבוע, mum kavua, then those words
could never have given it that sanctity because it was already excluded.
So what type of a sanctity did it get? It got sanctity
as if you said I'm donating this as a gift to the
temple treasury, בדק הבית. bedek habayit. So it never had a status
of a קורבן, korban, it always had a status of just goods
transferred to the הקדש hekdesh treasury. Okay, קדושת בדק הבית. kedushat bedek
habayit. No, no, no. And that's not enough. There it's because the
difference is that there's often, again, these are not identical concepts but
they're similar, that's not also as a general rule considered קדושת הגוף.
kedushat haguf. קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf is you're going to use the
object itself. I'm going to use this cow and bring it as
a קורבן, korban, I'm going to use this sheep and bring it
as a קורבן. korban. קדושת דמים kedushat damim means I don't really
care about the object. The object is not, it's not that its
whole identity is going to be used as this object in the
בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. I only see it, you know what they
say, don't they say what is it, a cynic knows the price
of everything but the value of nothing? Okay, so קדושת בדק הבית
kedushat bedek habayit only knows the price of things, not the value
of things. קדושת בדק הבית kedushat bedek habayit says, oh, you donated
your cow, how much is it worth? You donated your car, how
much is it worth? How much can I sell it, how much
can we get that money for? So that is the type of
קדושה kedusha you give this animal even if you're trying to make
it a קורבן korban if it has a מום. mum. And therefore
it never got that its identity as a cow was sanctified. It
was only owned for the sake of its value and therefore this,
it never gets into these categories which lead to exclusions because it
never had this קדושה kedusha of a קורבן. korban. Okay, so let's
take a look now. כל הקדשים שקדם מום קבוע להקדשם, kol hakodashim
shekodam mum kavua lehekdesham, so you have a permanent blemish preceded their
sanctification, so therefore when they were sanctified they never had the קדושה
kedusha of a קורבן, korban, ונפדו, venifdu, then you redeem it because
that's always what you would do with something that was only sanctified
for the treasury. The whole point is that you sell it and
you get the proceeds.
And use the שור shor to do חרישה charisha with?
Not until you redeem it. It's now owned by the בית המקדש.
beit hamikdash.
I know, meaning the בית המקדש beit hamikdash can use the שור.
shor. If it wanted to, yes, but normally they would just redeem
it, they would sell it. חייבים בבכורה, chayavim bevichora, so now that
its sanctity has been removed, it doesn't have any residual sanctity, it
never had the קדושה kedusha of a קורבן, korban, and because of
that it's not excluded from any laws. It's like it goes totally
back to the way it originally was. So therefore if it gives
birth to a בכור, bechor, that has the status of a
בכור. bechor. ובמתנות, uvematanot, if now you שחט shacht it, so then
you give from the arm and the, you know, and the stomach,
you give those gifts to the כהן. kohen. ויוצאים לחולין להיגזז ולהיעבד.
veyotzim lechulin lehiggazez ulehe'aved. Now this is important. The Torah says,
whatever,
okay, the Torah, we'll worry about it, forget it, fine. The Torah
said, okay, לא תעבוד בבכור שורך ולא תגוז בכור צאנך, lo ta'avod
bivchor shorecha velo tagoz bechor tzonecha, okay, don't work your firstborn, your
בכור, bechor, whether it's a cow, don't shear the firstborn of your
sheep. It also says that if you have a sacrifice that had
a מום mum and you redeemed it, that it says okay, then
you can slaughter it and eat it. But the חז"ל chazal understand
and we understand that what you do with an animal that had
a מום mum that you redeemed that was a sacrifice is it
still has some residual קדושה. kedusha. And what you're not allowed to
do by an animal that once was a sacrifice is you're not
allowed to shear it, you're not allowed to work it, all you
can do is slaughter it and eat it if it once was
a sacrifice.
You're not allowed to sell it like it's meat in the market?
Right, yes. So those things, so therefore it's saying that is only
by an animal that once was a sacrifice. This animal that was
never had the sanctity of a sacrifice was always just owned by
the temple treasury but never had the sanctity of a sacrifice, once
you redeem it, it's completely חולין chulin and you can do whatever
you want with it. You can shear it, you can work it,
you can do whatever you want with it. Okay, so it says,
where were we? ולדן וחלבן מותר, vladan vechalban mutar, also So let's
say they have children or let's say you milk them. If it
was an animal that was once a sacrifice and now it had
a child or you milked it, that child and that milk would
also be sanctified it would not be able to be used, whereas
if it were never a sacrifice, it was owned by the Temple
treasury and then redeemed, then anything now that it's been redeemed that
it produces you can benefit from. So basically on the one hand
you can use it, you can work it, you can shear it,
you can use it, and the products that come from it, the
children and the milk are also permissible.
Okay, and
if it was a regular קרבן korban you couldn't use the milk?
Correct. Okay, and we'll talk about all this in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, לאחר פדיונם, l'achar pidyonam, after you've redeemed it. והשוחטן בחוץ פטור,
vehashochtan bachutz patur, if you slaughtered this animal out of the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you would not transgress for bringing a קרבן korban
out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash because it isn't a קרבן,
korban, right? If I basically sanctified my cat to the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and I slaughtered it, okay, it wouldn't be a nice
thing, but I would have destroyed property of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash but it would not be the sin of bringing a קרבן
korban out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So although this is
a cow, because it never had the sanctity of a קרבן, korban,
I do not transgress. It's owned by the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
but I don't transgress for bringing a קרבן korban outside the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ואין עושין תמורה. v'ein osin tmura. Now, if you
remember the תורה Torah says that if you sanctify an animal as
a קרבן, korban, לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר אתו טוב ברע או רע
בטוב. lo yachalifenu v'lo yamir oto tov b'ra o ra b'tov. Don't
try to exchange the קדושה, kedusha, don't try to substitute it with
another animal, and if you try to substitute it with another animal
says והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קדש. v'haya hu utmurato yihye kodesh. Both
the original animal and the one you tried to substitute it with,
the תמורה, tmura, both are sanctified. That is only by an animal
that had the sanctity of a קרבן. korban. If I basically sanctify
my car and then I say actually I'd rather give this other
car to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, I'm going to try to
transfer the קדושה, kedusha, there's no law of תמורה. tmura. Okay, there
is no law of that now both cars become קדש. kodesh. Okay,
so the concept of תמורה tmura only applies to קרבנות korbanot and
since this cow always had a blemish, it never is considered to
be in the category of a קרבן. korban. ואם מתו יפדו. v'im
mesu yifdu. And if this cow dies, I can redeem it. Now,
why would that not be true if it had the sanctity of
a קרבן? korban? For two reasons. Number one is that there's a
principle that you don't redeem קרבנות korbanot in order to feed them
to the dogs. So if this cow died, what am I going
to be able to do with it if I redeem it? It's
a נבלה. neveila. I can't eat it. So what can I do?
I'll feed it to my dog, so I'll use it as dog
food. You don't redeem קרבנות korbanot to use them as dog food.
That's אין פודין את הקדשים להאכילם לכלבים. ein podin et hakodashim l'hachilam
l'klavim. That's again only by קרבנות korbanot which have this intrinsic קדושה.
kedusha. If this whole thing is here just for its money, for
its price, then okay, it died, at least let me salvage a
few bucks out of it, let the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash get
the ten dollars it can get and it's not really such a
problem what somebody's going to do with it because it was never
seen of as having intrinsic קדושה. kedusha. It was always just owned
for its value. So I can redeem it even if it's going
to be used as dog food. The other possible question of redeeming
it is that the תורה Torah speaks about when you sanctify an
animal and it has a blemish and you redeem it, it says
והעמידו לפני הכהן והעריכו לפני הכהן v'he'emido lifnei hakohen v'he'ericho lifnei hakohen
והעמידו לפני השם והעריכו לפני הכהן. v'he'emido lifnei Hashem v'he'ericho lifnei hakohen.
You stand the animal up and you assess its value. So from
there it's a concept of
בעינן העמדה והערכה. ba'inan ha'amada v'ha'aracha. You need to make it stand
and then assess its value. So that is only that has to
be alive and standing is only said by is only by קרבנות,
korbanot, not by non-קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so basically the upshot of all
of this is, I know we moved very quickly into an area
that we did not think we were going to go to, but
nevertheless, the upshot is is that when an animal was sanctified and
it starts with a blemish, it never was sanctified as a קרבן
korban even if you tried to make it a קרבן. korban. It
was only sanctified like you would sanctify your car. Its value was
owned by the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Therefore when it's redeemed, it
is totally non-sanctified anymore. It's just a transaction. It went into the
בית המקדש's Beis Hamikdash treasury, out of the בית המקדש's Beis Hamikdash
treasury. It doesn't have any residual thing because its identity was never
defined by the קדושה. kedusha. It was just primarily an issue of
ownership. And because the ownership has changed, it's totally back to where
it was and has no exclusions and so on. That's if it
started with a blemish. Okay, but חוץ מן הבכור ומן המעשר. chutz
min habechor u'min hamaser. The two there are the exception of a
בכור bechor and מעשר. maser. If you have a animal that I
sanctified to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and then let's say it
what would be the example of
hold on one second
right so let's say let's say what I did was here I
I had an animal that was pregnant okay and or even better
I sanctified the fetus that was in the womb of an animal
and then the mother gave birth to it and it became a
בכור bechor sorry not sanctified I'm confused start again let's say right
let's say an animal a fetus that was in the mother's womb
had a blemish Okay, and then it was born as a בכור.
bechor. Okay, so that's a case where
you don't know it had
a blemish while it was, well, it's coming out, let's say it
comes out missing a leg, genetic, a genetic right, right, right, right,
you
don't know beforehand.
Well, no, but now when it's coming out of the mother, you
see that it was born and it, you know, grew with a
blemish, deformed. Okay, so there the blemish preceded the sanctity. So according
to our משנה, Mishnah, if the blemish preceded the sanctity, it never
has the קדושה kedushah of a קרבן. korban. But the point is
that by a בכור, bechor, the sanctity and identity of a בכור
bechor קרבן korban is not something that you're placing on it, it's
something that comes naturally through being born, and therefore we understand that
its identity as a בכור bechor is regardless of the fact that
it had a blemish that preceded it. So if it had a
blemish and it was born as a בכור, bechor, it actually would
have the קדושה kedushah of a קרבן. korban. It can't be brought
because it has a blemish, but although the blemish preceded, the status
of בכור bechor is imposed on it regardless. Similarly, the idea of
giving the tenth מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. You take all of your
new animals, you put them in a pen, you count them, all
the ones that were born this year, you count them, and the
tenth one, it says העשירי, ha'asiri, the tenth one יהיה קדש, yihyeh
kodesh, is holy. And therefore is a קרבן. korban. Let's say that
tenth one that walks out of the pen that you count as
number ten happens to have a blemish. Does it only get the
status of בדק הבית? bedek habayis? No, this משנה Mishnah says that
this idea is not just something that became a קרבן korban because
you verbally designated it, but it becomes a קרבן korban by the
virtue of being born or by the virtue of walking out as
the tenth animal. That therefore forces that position, that identity of קרבן
korban on it, although it can't be brought because of the blemish,
it still has that status of a קרבן. korban.
But there could have been another one. I mean, at least a
בכור bechor you know like this is going to be the one.
Right, but we learned that from פסוקים pesukim that העשירי ha'asiri יהיה
קדש yihyeh kodesh regardless of if it has a blemish. So you
don't bring it as a sacrifice, but it has the קדושה kedushah
of a קרבן. korban. Okay, yes.
But doesn't a בכור bechor have to be a male?
Yes, but the male, it's a male that comes out.
You're counting the...
No, not the tenth. The tenth of the new animals is not
בכור, bechor, that's a different category. That's מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. The
tenth of all of the new animals that are born, you count
and you give to a כהן.
kohen. Because there's everything else left, right? What? After you take out
all the בכורות? bechorot? Yeah, you take a tenth of everything else
left, right? Is that what you're getting at?
I think you're conflating the two. There's one thing of the בכור,
bechor, which is the firstborn if it's a male, and there's another
thing of you take all of the newly born animals, not necessarily
firstborn, all of the newly born animals that year and you count
them and every tenth one is a קרבן. korban. That's מעשר בהמה.
ma'aser behemah. Okay, so that is the principle that if the blemish
preceded, it never gets קדושת קרבן kedushas korban with the exception of
בכור bechor and מעשר. ma'aser. Now, כל שקדם הקדשן את מומם. kol
shekadam hekdeshan es mumam.
Let's say first they were sanctified and then they got the blemish.
או מום עובר קודם הקדשן. o mum over kodem hekdeshan. Or first
they had a transient blemish, which does not really have the status
of a blemish because, you know, you can't bring an animal when
it has a transient blemish, you can't bring it as a קרבן,
korban, but it does not change its identity because it's something that
can
change. So if it only has a transient blemish, it does not
prevent the sanctity of it being a קרבן. korban. Okay, because that
is something that is not permanently part of its identity. So if
it had a transient blemish that preceded its being sanctified, ואחר כך
נולד להם מום קבוע, ve'achar kach nolad lahem mum kavua, and then
you sanctified it and then it got its permanent blemish, so it's
really a variation of the first case, but it means that the
permanent blemish occurred after it was sanctified. So when it was sanctified,
it had the full sanctity of a קרבן korban and only now
it got a problem that won't allow it to be brought. So
it has the sanctity of a קרבן korban that cannot be brought.
Now that it has the sanctity of a קרבן, korban, all these
rules apply to it. So in that case, ונפדו, venifdu, and now
it was redeemed, so פטורים מן הבכורה, peturim min habechorah, if it
has a firstborn child, you don't give a בכור bechor from it
because this still has the residual קדושה kedushah of a קרבן korban
to it, it was once a קרבן. korban. ומן המתנות, umin hamatanot,
you do not give זרוע ולחיים וקיבה zero'a velichayayim vekeivah if you
שחט shecht it and eat it. ואינם יוצאים לחולין להיגזז ולהיעבד, ve'einam
yotzim lechulin lehiggazez ulehe'aved, it's not fully
desacralized, you cannot shear
it
and
work it. וולדן וחלבן אסור, uveladan vechalban assur, you cannot benefit from
its children or from its milk, לאחר פדיונם le'achar pidyonam even after
you've redeemed it. והשוחטן בחוץ חייב, vehashochtan bachutz chayav, if you slaughter
it out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you transgress because it
has the קדושה kedushah of a קרבן. korban. And... ועושים ve'osim I
know what you're gonna I'll get back to you in a minute,
ועושים תמורה, ve'osim temurah, you can if you try to exchange it
with another animal then the other animal becomes קדוש, kadosh, it has
the laws of תמורה temurah because it has the sanctity of a
קרבן, korban, this is before you've redeemed it. ואם מתו יקברו. ve'im
mesu yikkaveru. So the last couple of cases is before you've redeemed
it. While you have not yet redeemed it, if you שחט shecht
it out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you're חייב chayav for
bringing a קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash if
it still has the full קדושה kedushah of a קרבן. korban. If
you try to transfer the קדושה, kedushah, both become קדוש, kadosh, that's
תמורה, temurah, and if it dies you can't redeem it. Why not?
Because that would be redeeming it as dog food. In order to
use it as dog food, or the other reason is just a
text ...technical requirement that it have to be need העמדה והערכה, ha'amadah
v'ha'arachah, needs to be stood up in order to be redeemed. Now
Michael is going to ask about the case of שחיטה shechting it
out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. What are you going to
ask, Michael? Go ahead. Okay, which is: who cares that it has
the קדושה kedusha of a קרבן, korban, if it has a blemish,
then you can't bring it as a קרבן, korban, and you're only
חייב chayav for a קרבן korban out of the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash if it could have been brought in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. So that's a question that the גמרא Gemara asks, to which
the גמרא Gemara answers, it's not the greatest answer, but the גמרא
Gemara says we're talking about a very special case that it's a
type of a blemish that is only like cataracts of the eye,
which is not so obvious, and that has a special status that
if it's brought as a קרבן korban and put on the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, you wouldn't take it off. So with that type of a
blemish, it's technically a blemish and allows it to be redeemed and
all of that, but because בדיעבד bedi'eved it would be accepted as
a קרבן, korban, you would be חייב chayav if you brought it
out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, but the basic point
is with all of these, is that if the blemish comes later,
although that allows it to be redeemed and prevents it from being
brought as a קרבן, korban, since the קדושה kedusha came first, it
defines its identity as a קרבן korban and now all of these
excluded laws apply. When it has the קדושה, kedusha, even after the
קדושה kedusha is removed, it's redeemed, it has that residual aspect of
קדושה, kedusha, you can't shear it, you can't work it, you only
שחט shecht it to eat it, and so on, and then you
don't use the milk, and therefore all of these other exclusions apply,
that it doesn't have the law of the firstborn, you don't give
the gifts of זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim vekeivah, all of that
is when it started with the קדושה kedusha of קרבן korban even
though it's redeemed. But if it was originally excluded, it never got
the קדושה kedusha of a קרבן, korban, then and it only got
was owned by the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, then all these special
laws do not apply.
Are those last three after it was redeemed?
No, the last three are before it was redeemed, because it says,
because it's preceded by the phrase לאחר פדיונם. le'achar pidyonam. ולד וחלב
אסור לאחר פדיונם, Velad vechalav asur le'achar pidyonam, and then it's shifting
back to its status before it was redeemed.
Okay, you want to say how we know all these things?
More or less, between here and בכורות, Bechoros, yes. Let's take a
look now at the גמרא Gemara getting us back to the זרוע
לחיים וקיבה. zero'a lechayayim vekeivah. So טעמא דכתב רחמנא אותם. ta'ama dechasav
rachmana osam.
The reason we know that you don't give the חזה ושוק chazeh
vehashok by a קרבן, korban, by going back to the first half
of the משנה. Mishnah. Why by a קרבן korban you only give
the חזה ושוק, chazeh vehashok, the breast and the thigh, and not
the זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim vekeivah, is because the verse said
זה, zeh, that by קרבן korban only they, only the חזה ושוק
chazeh veshok go to the כהנים, kohanim, not the other gifts. הלאו
הכי, Halav hachi,
had the verse not said that, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would
have thought, קדשים חייבים במתנות, kodshim chayavim bematanos, that even if it's
a קרבן korban you give the זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim vekeivah,
that's the קל וחומר kal vachomer that the משנה Mishnah wanted to
make. If you give one gift, you should give the other gift.
If you give the חזה ושוק, chazeh veshok, then you should certainly
give the other gifts, and it only excluded that because of a
פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא Gemara said, one minute, איכא למפרך, ika
lemifrach, you can challenge that. מה חולין שכן חייבים בבכורה. Mah lechullin
shekein chayavim bebechorah.
So you said, oh, here is the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If
by non-קרבנות korbanos you give the זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim vekeivah,
how much more so should you give it by a קרבן korban
that you're already giving other gifts, the חזה ושוק. chazeh veshok. So
besides that that's funny itself, because you're giving other gifts maybe you
shouldn't give this gift, but the גמרא Gemara says, but anyway I
could challenge that קל וחומר. kal vachomer. I could say maybe there's
something that makes non-קרבנות korbanos weightier that demands that you give more
gifts by non-קרבנות korbanos than by קרבנות. korbanos. How do I know
that? It says, well consider the firstborn. We just learned in the
משנה Mishnah that you only give a בכור bechor if it's born
to an animal that's not a קרבן. korban. You don't give the
בכור bechor if it's born to an animal that is a קרבן.
korban. So you see that by non-קרבנות korbanos you give more gifts
than you give by קרבנות. korbanos. So what type of קל וחומר
kal vachomer is this? Okay, so it says, מה חולין שכן חייב
בבכורה, mah lechullin shekein chayav bebechorah, so of course you're going to
give this gift more by non-קרבנות. korbanos. You give other gifts more
by non-קרבנות, korbanos, like the בכור. bechor. So the גמרא Gemara said,
oh, תיתי מזכרים, teisei mizecharim, I could have still made the קל
וחומר kal vachomer from male animals. When it comes to a male
cow, I guess you wouldn't say a male cow, when it comes
to a bull, or when it comes to a sheep, right, a
male sheep, a ram, so there you never give firstborn from them,
they're male. And you nevertheless you give זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim
vekeivah, how much more so should you give it at least in
the case of, you know, by קרבנות, korbanos, certainly by male קרבנות.
korbanos. But anyway we'll use the קל וחומר kal vachomer from a
type of חולין, chullin, a type of non-קרבן korban that you would
not give the gift of the בכור. bechor. So the גמרא Gemara
says, but there are other gifts you give by
חולין. chullin. מה זכרים שכן חייבים בראשית הגז. Mah zecharim shekein chayavim
bereishis hageiz. How about the fact that you give the ראשית הגז
reishis hageiz by non-קרבן korban and you don't give it by קרבנות.
korbanos. So again, the קל וחומר kal vachomer is if you give
this by this gift by non-קרבן korban you should certainly give it
by קרבנות. korbanos. The counterargument is what are you talking about? There
are plenty of gifts you give by non-קרבן korban not by קרבנות,
korbanos, בכור. bechor. Okay, we're talking about males. Males you don't give
that. Okay, but you give ראשית הגז, reishis hageiz, you don't give
ראשית הגז reishis hageiz by קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ah, one minute, the גמרא Gemara says, מתישים, mityashim, I'll bring the
proof from from male goats, where there aren't shearings. Okay, so by
a male goat you don't give gifts as a non-קרבן, korban, you
give a gift as a קרבן, korban, so it's a
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, right, that if you're giving a gift
by... No, there're
gifts, there's still a gift that you give by male goats that
you don't give by, by their קרבן korban counterpart. What is it?
מעשר בהמה. maiser beheima. All the new goats that are born that
year, every tenth one is given as a, as a קרבן מעשר
בהמה. korban maiser beheima. So again, there are more gifts that you
give by a non-קרבן korban than you give by a קרבן. korban.
So the גמרא Gemara says מזקנים. mizkeinim. Okay, we'll prove it from
old male goats. Doesn't literally mean old, it means that they're a
year old, meaning that they, they are not newly born. You only
give מעשר בהמה maiser beheima from the newly born animals. So it
says I have one type of non-קרבן korban that there's no gifts
that you give from it. What is that? A male, so therefore
no בכור, bechor, goat, no shearings, that is more than a year
old, and therefore you don't give מעשר בהמה, maiser beheima, you don't
give any gifts from that, and you still give זרוע לחיים וקיבה.
zroa lechayayim vekeiva. So if you give it in that case, you
should certainly give it by a קרבן, korban, which you give the
other gifts from. Okay, so that's the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, מה לזקנים
שכן נכנסו לדיר להתעשר. mah lizkeinim shekein nichnasu lidyar lihitaseir. It might
be that if it's more than a year old, then you don't,
you don't have any remainder gift that you give from it, but
you did, it was, had, it was part of a group of
animals from which you gave a gift when it was still a
year, when it was still under a year. It did go into
the pen for מעשר maiser when it, when it started its life,
so it's at least in that category of something you would have
given a gift from, even though now it's outgrown it.
So the גמרא Gemara says, where are we? Okay, מלקוח ויתום. milakuach
veyasom. No, if it's the animal, if I purchased this male goat,
or it was an orphan, its mother died in childbirth, so because
as an orphan, by the way, right, why is that relevant? Because
the פסוק pasuk says שבעת ימים תהיה תחת אמו ומיום השמיני והלאה
ירצה לקרבן אשה לה', shivat yamim tihiyeh tachat imo umiyom hashmini vahala
yeiratzeh lekorban isheh laHashem, that an animal is with its mother for
seven days. So if the mother dies, people, it's exactly interesting here,
חז"ל Chazal really understood this verse literally, if the mother dies before
the animal is eight days old, you can't use the animal as
a קרבן. korban.
So if this animal is an orphan, or if it was purchased,
it wasn't born in your flock, you purchased it, you would not
include it in the group of things you would give מעשר maiser
for. Okay, so therefore the גמרא Gemara says I can still get
you a case of a חולין, chullin, a non-קרבן korban that you
give no gifts from.
Even if it's six months old?
Yes. It's only if it's born in your flock. A goat, a
male goat that you purchased, that because it's male there's no בכור,
bechor, because it's a goat there's no shearing, because you purchased it
or it's an orphan, there'll never be מעשר בהמה, maiser beheima, and
that is a type of a חולין chullin that there's no other
gifts, but you give זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zroa lechayayim vekeiva. So how
much more so should you give it by a קרבן korban which
has some gifts?
I said it by זקנים, zkeinim, right?
What? You can say זקנים, zkeinim, זקנים zkeinim at least were once
in that category.
But I'm saying you don't need to say it for the זקנים,
zkeinim, it's a male goat but זקנים. zkeinim.
Right, we're dropping the זקנים. zkeinim. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, מה ללקוח ויתום שכן נכנסים במינם
לדיר להתעשר. mah lilakuach veyasom shekein nichnasim beminam lidyar lihitaseir. Still in
their type of animal, maybe this particular case there are no gifts,
but this type of animal, goats and whatever, you do give gifts
from, you give מעשר בהמה maiser beheima from. The גמרא Gemara says
במינם קאמרת? beminam kaamart? What, that's your question? In their species you
give gifts? קדשים נמי במינם נכנסים לדיר להתעשר. kodashim nami beminam nichnasim
lidyar lihitaseir. It's also then true by a קרבן. korban. All these
things you mentioned that don't apply by a קרבן, korban, בכור, bechor,
מעשר, maiser, they apply by the species of animals, they apply by
sheep and cows and goats. So the fact that it applies by
the species is not relevant. We're talking about the specific instantiation. Okay,
so therefore what the קל וחומר kal vachomer is, there's a type
of a חולין chullin that you give no gifts from other than
זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zroa lechayayim vekeiva, which is it? A male goat
that you bought as a child,
okay, that's orphan or that you bought. So you give no gifts
from, but you still give זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zroa lechayayim vekeiva. So
how much more so should you give it in the case of
a קרבן korban where you're also giving the חזה chazeh and the
שוק? shok? And therefore we needed the
פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so, so fine, the גמרא Gemara says fine, I
accept it. So now we've established that there was a reason to
think you would give זרוע לחיים וקיבה zroa lechayayim vekeiva by a
קרבן korban and you needed the פסוק pasuk to exclude it. But
now that the פסוק pasuk has excluded it and I know you
don't give זרוע לחיים וקיבה zroa lechayayim vekeiva by a קרבן, korban,
let me flip it and argue that by חולין chullin you should
give חזה chazeh and שוק. shok. Right, that, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this, ואיהו חולין חייבין בחזה ושוק. veihu chullin chayavin bechazeh
veshok. Fine, we've established קרבן korban is only חזה chazeh and שוק,
shok, not זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zroa lechayayim vekeiva. Now let's go the
opposite way. Why not demand that I give a חזה chazeh and
a שוק shok by חולין, chullin, the, the breast and the thigh?
מקל וחומר. mikal vachomer. What's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? ומה קדשים
שאין חייבין במתנות, umah kodashim sheein chayavin bematanot, קרבנות korbanot as we've
already seen as a general rule you give no gifts from the
קרבנות korbanot other than the חזה chazeh and
שוק, shok, and
nevertheless חייבין בחזה ושוק. chayavin bechazeh veshok. so you give all these
gifts to the כהנים kohanim from non-קרבנות, korbanot, אינו דין שחייבים בחזה
ושוק, aino din she-chayavim be-chaze ve-shok, how much more so should I
give this gift that we find by the קרבנות, korbanot, I should
maybe have to give the חזה chaze and the שוק shok as
well.
אמר קרא, Amar kra, the verse says, וזה, veze, this is the
first by what do you call it, by
our, by the זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim vekeivah, וזה יהיה משפט
הכהנים, veze yihiyeh mishpat hakohanim, this is the rule of the כהנים,
kohanim, the gift of the כהנים. kohanim. זה אין מידי אחריני לא,
Ze in, midei achrini lo, only this is what they get from
the non-קרבן. korban. From the non-קרבן korban they just get the זרוע
לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim vekeivah, they do not get the חזה ושוק.
chaze ve-shok. So we have another verse, we have a verse that
excludes the זרוע לחיים וקיבה zero'a lechayayim vekeivah from a קרבן korban
and the verse that excludes the חזה ושוק chaze ve-shok from a
non-קרבן. korban. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, why did
I even need a verse? אלא טעמא דכתב רחמנא זה, Ella ta'ama
dekata rachmana ze, the reason you're saying that we know don't give
the חזה ושוק chaze ve-shok is the תורה Torah says זה. ze.
הלאו הכי, Halav hachi, had it not been for that verse, הוה
אמינא חולין חייבים בחזה ושוק, hava amina chullin chayavim be-chaze ve-shok, that
maybe I should say give the חזה chaze and the שוק shok
from the חולין. chullin. הוה בעי תנופה, Hava bayei tenufah, how could
you do that? The way you give the חזה ושוק, chaze ve-shok,
the גמרא Gemara says, the תורה Torah says is through this ritual
of waving it, right? And then giving it to the כהן. kohen.
You okay, Bobby?
Yeah.
So
it says you need to wave it. היכא לינפיהו, Heicha linufeihu,
where should you do this ritual of waving? I mean we're not
just going to give it straight, if we're going to say we
apply it to a non-קרבן, korban, we're going to take the way
it was given as a קרבן korban and do the same thing
by a non-קרבן. korban. Well, the way it's given as a קרבן,
korban, the חזה ושוק, chaze ve-shok, it's waved before God and given
to the כהן. kohen. So where are you going to wave this
thing if it's a non-קרבן? korban?
היכא לינפיהו. Heicha linufeihu. אי אבאי, Ee abai, if it's outside the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, לפני ה' כתיב, lifnei Hashem ketiv, it says
you wave this חזה ושוק chaze ve-shok before God. אי אגבאי, Ee
agabai, so maybe every time I שחט shecht a cow in wherever
I am, if I'm in New Jersey or in Tel Aviv or
in Eilat, I have to bring the חזה ושוק chaze ve-shok to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and wave it and give it to
the כהנים. kohanim. That's what I would have thought if I would
have made this קל וחומר kal vachomer and applied it to
non-קרבן. korban. Stay hot as everywhere. Okay, well, good point. So anyway,
alright, touché. So קמעייל חולין לעזרה, kama'ei chullin la'azarah, you can't do
that. It's a non-קרבן, korban, you can't bring a non-קרבן korban in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and give it and do a קרבן-like
korban ritual with it. Okay, I mean תוספות Tosafot discusses that maybe
you're able to do bring חולין chullin for other purposes, maybe the
כהן kohen could eat, you know, could eat some, could bring, you
know, could eat some other food together with his קרבן, korban, but
you can't bring a non-קרבן korban and do קרבן-like korban rituals with
it in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. That's חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah.
So therefore what, what, you would never have thought you could do
a חזה ושוק chaze ve-shok by a non-קרבן. korban. It's a קרבן
korban ritual. You're not going to do a קרבן korban ritual out
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you're not going to do
a קרבן korban ritual in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash with a
non-קרבן. korban. So therefore why did you even need a פסוק? pasuk?
No, it's a קרבן korban ritual just for קרבנות, korbanot, so for
non-קרבן korban you don't need to do anything.
No, because we, because we're assuming that if you're going to learn
it up from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, then you're going to
learn it the same way. It's going to be the same thing
that you're going to apply, you're not going to change it. So
the גמרא Gemara says הילכך לא אפשר, hilkach lo efshar, it never
was possible. אלא, Ella, you're right, forget it, I never would have
thought you could have given the חזה ושוק, chaze ve-shok, I don't
need a פסוק, pasuk, of course it's absurd. It's a קרבן korban
ritual and I never would have applied it to a non-קרבן. korban.
אלא זה למה לי, Ella ze lama li, and now we're shifting
gears. Now we've figured out the משנה, mishnah, you don't give the
זרוע לחיים וקיבה zero'a lechayayim vekeivah to a קרבן, korban, you don't
give חזה ושוק chaze ve-shok to a non-קרבן, korban, certainly that's a
קרבן korban ritual, a קרבן korban gift, you don't give it by
a non-קרבן. korban. Now we just have another question, which is the
פסוק pasuk says וזה יהיה משפט הכהנים, veze yihiyeh mishpat hakohanim, this
is the law of the כהנים kohanim by this זרוע לחיים וקיבה,
zero'a lechayayim vekeivah, and what does the word זה ze teach us?
And now we're going to introduce a concept which we're going to
stay focused on for the rest of today and for tomorrow. So
let's take a look. אלא זה למה לי, Ella ze lama li,
so now we're switching gears. What's the meaning of the word זה?
ze? So לכדרב חסדא, lich'derav Chisda, like רב חסדא's Rav Chisda teaching.
דאמר רב חסדא, D'amar Rav Chisda, המזיק מתנות כהונה או שאכלן פטור
מלשלם, hamazik matnot kehunah o she'achalan patur milishalem, if I took a
gift that's going to the כהן, kohen, which could include the זרוע
לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim vekeivah, it could include the ראשית הגז, reishit
hagez, the first shearings, it could include תרומה. terumah. Well, תרומה's terumah
a funny category. Let's say מעשר, ma'aser, which doesn't exactly go to
the כהן, kohen, but whatever, לוי, Levi, okay, and I went ahead
and I destroyed it or I ate it, so what would you
say? Who do I pay? So רב חסדא Rav Chisda says you
don't pay anybody because it's, now there's two possible reasons. What? One
is just even without a פסוק, pasuk, there's nobody, you know, what
are you going to do? You need to get a class action
suit together, right? Because who is the כהן kohen that I stole
from? That is not a particular כהן. kohen. Any כהן kohen that
comes to me, I could say I wasn't going to give it
to you. So that's a principle called ממון שאין לו תובעין. mammon
she'ein lo tovin. There's nobody who can demand it because there's no
particular כהן kohen to whom, who owns it. Okay, and you don't
have this idea of like a class action suit, okay, and that
they were hurt as a class even though they weren't hurt as
individuals. You don't have that. So there's no individual who can demand
it. Now that really means conceptually, if that's the point, I really
did injure them, but technically there's no way that they can bring
me to court because there's no particular person that I've injured. That's
the ממון שאין לו תובעין mamon she'ein lo tovin principle. But there's
another way of excluding it based on the פסוק pasuk of זה.
zeh. זה יהיה משפט הכהנים Zeh yihiyeh mishpat hakohanim means give it
when it's in present. If it's here and it's physically present, you
have to give it. If it's not physically present, if it's not
זה, zeh, if it's not this thing here that's physically present, then
you don't have an obligation. If it's been destroyed, you don't have
an obligation. Now that says something conceptually very different. That says that
when I separate out, let's say, my ראשית הגז, reishit hagez, I
haven't given it yet to the כהן, Kohen, and I separate out
my זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zeroa lechayayim vekeivah, what's the status of this
right now? Who owns this? Who owns this ראשית הגז reishit hagez
right now before I've given it to the כהן? Kohen? So there's
two possibilities. I own it until I hand it over to the
כהן Kohen and I have a מצוה mitzvah to hand it to
the כהן, Kohen, but until I do, I own it. And the
other possibility is that as soon as I separate it out, it's
owned by the collective כהנים Kohanim and my role at that point
is to designate, I have the right to designate which כהן Kohen
gets it, but it automatically is owned already by the group, by
the collective of the כהנים. Kohanim. So that is really two ways
of explaining why when I damage it, I don't pay. They really
reflect these two different understandings. One is saying it's owned by the
collective of the כהנים, Kohanim, I've damaged כהנים's Kohanim's property, but they
have no way to bring me to
court, ממון שאין לו תובעין. mamon she'ein lo tovin. The other way
is I haven't damaged their property yet, it's my property. What I've
done is I've gotten myself out of the מצוה mitzvah to give
them something,
but at the moment that I damaged it, I was damaging my
property. It's just that now since it's not around, I no longer
have a מצוה mitzvah to give them that. I got out of
the מצוה, mitzvah, but I didn't damage their property. Two very different
ways of understanding. One is based on the פסוק pasuk זה zeh
and the other is regardless of the פסוק, pasuk,
but using the פסוק pasuk really makes the point that they don't
own it yet, as opposed to without that, they own it but
they can't demand compensation.
Would you say that even if I understand the collective thing, but
let's say I actually designated it for a specific כהן Kohen and
let's say I say, "Rabbi, please give this מעשר ma'aser to the
לוי Levi over there," and then David comes and eats it along
the way.
So that's an interesting question and it goes to a whole סוגיא
sugya about מכירי כהונה makirei kehuna and so on, if I have
a practice of giving it to a particular כהן. Kohen. Let's bracket
that for now. Let's assume that until a particular כהן Kohen actually
gets it, he doesn't own it yet. Okay, but that's a second
level question. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
In the second case, when does the obligation occur?
What do you mean?
So let's say you're shearing a sheep and then you have the
wool and you destroy it. Right. Before you destroy it, it's in
front of you. Yeah. Do you have the obligation?
Yes, you definitely have the obligation to give it. You definitely have
the obligation to give it and you've definitely subverted your מצוה, mitzvah,
but you haven't damaged somebody else's property because there's lots of ways
I can subvert a מצוה mitzvah without damaging somebody's property, right? So
that's the point. If it's based on the פסוק pasuk זה, zeh,
it says you have a מצוה mitzvah to give it and if
you destroy it, yes, you have subverted your מצוה, mitzvah, but you
haven't destroyed their property, okay?
But it doesn't say this is theirs.
No, it's saying this is what you give, but if it's not
here, you don't give anything. Okay.
Is there any
punishment
for subverting the מצוה? mitzvah?
No, in other words, outside of an actual punishment, that you owe
anything, is there some other?
Yeah, God will work on it with the accounting.
You've gotten out of a מצוה. mitzvah. Right. Okay, so גופא, gufa,
let's take a look. Let's go back and look at this. אמר
רב חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: המזיק מתנות כהונה, hamazik matnot kehuna, if
you damage gifts to כהן, Kohen, או שאכלן, o she'achalan, or you
ate them, פטור מלשלם, patur milishalem, you don't have to pay. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אי בעית אימא, I ba'it eima,
if you want I'll say, מדכתיב midikativ זה, zeh, this is what
you give, and there, as I said, more suggests that they don't
own it yet, so you've gotten out of a מצוה, mitzvah, you
only give it when it's around. ואי בעית אימא, Ve'i ba'it eima,
משום דהוה ליה ממון שאין לו תובעין, mishum dehavei lei mamon she'ein
lo tovin, it's money that has nobody who can demand compensation. You
did destroy their property, but nobody can demand compensation.
The גמרא Gemara will get to that.
מיתיבי: Meitivei: וזה יהיה משפט הכהנים, vezeh yihiyeh mishpat hakohanim, מלמד שהמתנות
דין. melamed shehamatnot din.
This is the law of the כהנים, Kohanim, so the ברייתא braita
says the gifts are a law, meaning a law somehow that it
can be something that the courts deal with. So if it's something
the courts deal with, it sounds like you can collect payment. למאי
הלכתא? Lema'i hilchata? For what purpose are we saying it's a court
issue? לאו להוציאו בדיינים? lav lehotzi'o bedayanim? Doesn't it suggest that if
you destroy it, it can be collected in the court? Now who
would have a right to collect? רש"י Rashi says maybe the first
person to file suit, but whoever it is, maybe this shows that
it's not a principle of ממון שאין לו תובעין, mamon she'ein lo
tovin, that even as a collective, somebody can go ahead and demand
payment because it says it applies to the courts. גמרא Gemara says:
לא, לחולקן בדיינים. lo, lechulkan bedayanim. No,
not to say that if you damaged it, somebody can get compensation,
but to say that when you are actually giving out the gifts,
the court will oversee or can control or direct how you give
out your gifts. What does that mean?
וכדרב שמואל בר נחמני, Uchedirav Shmuel bar Nachmani, like Rav Shmuel
bar Nachmani. How do you know you don't give the gifts of
the כהנים, kohanim, whether it's תרומה terumah or זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a
lechayayim vekeivah, whatever it might be? How do you know you don't
give it to a כהן kohen who's an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz,
who's a, you know, ignoramus? And here it does not just mean
intelligence עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, it also means somebody that is not
careful, punctilious with issues of observance. How do you know? שנאמר, Shene'emar,
there's a verse says ויאמר לעם ליושבי ירושלים, Vayomer la'am leyoshvei Yerushalayim,
and he said to the people, to those that dwelt in Jerusalem,
this is at רש"י Rashi says the context here יהושפט, Yehoshaphat, so
one of the latter kings of the first commonwealth, he said to
the
people לתת מנת הכהנים והלוויים, latet menat hakohanim vehaleviyim, הכהנים והלוויים, hakohanim
vehaleviyim, to give the gift of the כהנים kohanim and the לויים
leviyim למען יחזקו בתורת ה', lema'an yechezku betorat Hashem, that they should
strengthen or be strengthened in the Torah of God. כל המחזיק בתורת
ה', Kol hamachzik betorat Hashem, if you hold up God's Torah יש
לו מנת, yesh lo menat, then you are deserving of the gift.
ושאינו מחזיק בתורת ה', Veshe'eino machzik betorat Hashem, if you do not
אין לו מנת, ein lo menat, you should not give them the
gift. Now that does not mean that they, that you, if you
give them the gift they don't own it, or תוספות Tosafot even
says if there's nobody else around, you know, then you can give
it to them, but if you have a choice which כהן kohen
to give it to, you're supposed to give to the כהן kohen
that more truly represents God's Torah, which makes sense, you know, actually
there's something very nice about that because, you know, since the כהנים,
kohanim, it gets back to the discussion before, are so much functioning
in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, it's possible to be a functionary
in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and to not represent a real
sense of religious, you know, leadership or modeling religious values is, I
mean, we, you know, we know stories about that, בני עלי Bnei
Eli and so on, you know, that who could be good כהנים
kohanim in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash but not good כהנים kohanim
as religious models and leaders. So here it's saying that when you
give these gifts of the כהנים, kohanim, it's not just by virtue
of birthright and they're כהנים. kohanim. Part of the role of being
a כהן kohen is representing God and representing Torah, and therefore there
needs to be preference to give these gifts to those כהנים. kohanim.
So therefore when it says it's a law that applies to the
courts, it doesn't mean to collect if it's been damaged, it means
that the courts might, will oversee or might come to try to
correct or control if people are giving the gifts in what is
seen as a non-proper way, giving it to כהנים kohanim who do
not really deserve it.
Yes, this is actually, this opens the door for a lot of,
you know, putting the common person in a position of judging how
religious people are, and then you might leave a whole class of
people
without sustenance.
Right, right, that's an interesting point. Right, I mean it does sort
of say that the court is involved, so it's not just everybody
assesses, but you know, that's the flip side. I was trying to
frame it very positively, you know, I guess the point is like
there's this whole middle group, meaning there are people that are clearly
רשעים, resha'im, I think we can agree that those types of people
you're, you know, you know, that should not be getting these gifts,
right, but you're talking about the המון העם, hamon ha'am, the עמי
הארץ, amei ha'aretz, the people that maybe, right, that can easily be
mis-, you know, misjudged, or also you got a lot of people
that, right, don't maybe have the benefit of an education or of
an upbringing, right, right, and they need the support. Yeah, that's a,
that's a very legitimate point, you know. All our campaigns are basically
going to get...
Yeah, I don't know what to say about that. I mean, I
will say look, you know, that while the גמרא Gemara says it,
you know, I don't know how much evidence there was that actually
there was that type of selection that went on in practice. I
mean תוספות Tosafot is very quick to say that, you know, certainly
בדיעבד bedi'avad and certainly if there aren't other choices or whatever, and
again I don't know historically anyway, historically we have very little evidence
of this anyway because these gifts, you know...
The כהנים kohanim were corrupt anyhow right before...
Well right, I mean that's the positive part is that it's a
counteraction to the corruption and entitlement of the כהנים. kohanim. You know,
everything comes at a cost. All right, well let's see now as
the גמרא Gemara continues. No, you can't, no, I'm sorry, we have
five minutes left, you'll ask me later. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this, okay,
תא
שמע, ta shema, come and hear, רבי יהודה בן בתירא אומר, Rabbi
Yehuda ben Beteira omer, so we're still trying to figure out whether
you can collect if these are damaged. משפט, mishpat, it says this
is the law, מלמד שמתנות דין, melamed shematanot din,
that they are, that they are, you know, subject to, to law
of the courts. יכול אפילו חזה ושוק, Yachol afilu chazeh veshok, maybe
even the breast and the thigh of a קרבן korban have a
דין, din, are subject to the same law of the court? תלמוד
לומר זה, Talmud lomar zeh, no, only these, only the gifts of
the זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zero'a lechayayim vekeivah. So again we're saying what
does it mean that they're, that they're law? למאי, L'mai, for what
purpose?
אילימא לחוקו בדיינים, Ileima l'choko badayanim, that, that the judges oversee who
gets what like we said before, אתו חזה ושוק לאו בדיינים מחלקו?
atu chazeh veshok lav badayanim mechalku? So why are we excluding the
חזה chazeh and the שוק? shok? Presumably that same idea that it
only goes to deserving כהנים kohanim would apply even by the gifts
of the קרבנות. korbanot. Now I have to tell you that I
find that strange because the general rule of the gifts of the
קרבנות korbanot is that they're divided equally. Well no, the תורה Torah
makes it sound like it's the כהן kohen that does the... עבודה.
Avoda. But the גמרא Gemara says and the משנה Mishnah says that
basically it's all divided, it's all divided equally. So I'm not exactly
sure, you know, what, you know, that question over there. But anyway,
the גמרא Gemara doesn't want to say here that it's about the
court overseeing it, אלא לאו לאו ציוו בדיינים ela lav lo tzivu
bedayanim presumably it means that again if it's damaged that's whether you
can collect it or not. So it's not exactly clear why the
גמרא Gemara thinks that that would be different between these gifts and
the חזה ושוק, Chazeh veShok, but we'll bracket that for now. Let's
see what the גמרא Gemara answers. No, הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai
askinan what are we talking about says the גמרא Gemara דאתו לידיה.
de'asu liyadei. Yes, we are talking that it's that the court can
adjudicate it to get to get compensation if you damaged it, but
only after it was actually given to the כהן. Kohen. It was
given to the כהן Kohen and then you damaged it, then the
court will demand compensation. Now the question is twofold: why do you
need a פסוק pasuk to tell me that? Obviously once it's given
to him it's his. And number two, why would it be different
by the חזה ושוק? Chazeh veShok? Wouldn't I say the same thing,
that if you you damaged it once he got it that you
have to pay him? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אי דאתו לידיה ei de'asu liyadei if he already got it, מאי
למימרא mai lemimra then you know what's what's the חידוש? chiddush? Of
course if you damaged it once he got it you have to
pay him. So it says לאתו לידיה בטבליהו. le'asu liyadei betivlaihu. No,
he got it but you got he took it without while it
was still mixed up. What does that mean?
I שחט shacht my קרבן, korban, there's a כהן Kohen hovering around,
as soon as I שחט shacht my קרבן, korban, my cow, there's
a כהן Kohen hovering around, as soon as I שחט shacht my
cow he comes up and he picks up the whole cow, okay
it's a it's a sheep, he picks up the whole sheep and
he says I'm taking possession of the זרוע לחיים וקיבה. Zroa Lechayayim
veKeiva. So he took it, okay, רש"י Rashi says I was I
didn't even give it to him, he took it, and he took
it while it was still hadn't even yet been separated out. So
in that case I might think that he's not entitled to it,
he doesn't own it yet, it hasn't been separated out, I didn't
give it to him, that's the חידוש. chiddush. וקסבר האי תנא vekasavar
hai tanna and this תנא tanna holds מתנות שלא הורמו כמי שהורמו
דמיין matanos shelo hurmu kemi shehurmu damyan that even if I haven't
separated it it's like I separated it out and therefore even if
he grabs it he does get to keep it and therefore if
I damage it then I do have to pay, it is his.
Now why is that different than the
חזה ושוק? Chazeh veShok? So רש"י Rashi
says right so רש"י Rashi says that the חזה ושוק Chazeh veShok
is divided up by the כהנים Kohanim that work that week. So
if some כהן Kohen whose job it who was not working that
week burst into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and grabbed the חזה
ושוק, Chazeh veShok, you know, an analogous type of a case, he
wouldn't be entitled to it. So again, it's a very special circumstance.
What does it mean that it's applying by the court? It means
the court can collect if it's damaged, but not that in general
the court collects if I damage, it's after the כהן Kohen ran
and grabbed it, that he therefore does own it, but that is
by these gifts, not by the קרבנות Korbanos because the קרבנות Korbanos
if he's not working that week, you know, his grabbing has no
relevance. But by the gifts, even if I haven't separated it and
even if I haven't given it to him and he just came
and grabbed it, he would be entitled to it.
It goes to all the other כהנים. Kohanim. If you went and
grabbed it and you weren't working, they'd just take it back from
you and give it to all the other ones.
Exactly, exactly. Okay.
Why if it was separated he couldn't grab it?
No, he certainly could, but it wouldn't be as much of a
חידוש. chiddush. Even if it wasn't separated, even if he grabbed it.
Okay. So we still have not yet disproven this idea that you
cannot collect if it's been damaged. Let's try one more thing quickly.
תא שמע Ta shema come and hear: בעל הבית שהיה עובר ממקום
למקום Baal habayis shehaya over mimakom lemakom וצריך ליטול לקט שכחה ופאה
ומעשר עני. vetzarich litol leket shikcha upeah umaaser ani. So you have
somebody who has money, he's a homeowner, but he's now traveling and
he doesn't have any funds, there were no ATMs at that time,
right? So what is he going to do? So wherever he is,
he can get the gifts of the poor even though he actually
has wealth, but he has no money available, no food available, he
can get the the gleanings of the poor and the gifts and
the מעשר maaser of the poor. נוטל הוא notel hu he takes
it וכשיחזור ישלם vecheshayachzor yeshalem and when he gets back home then
he pays back the עניים, aniyim, the amount of funds that he
took, he gives as a donation to the poor. דברי רבי אליעזר.
divrei Rabbi Eliezer. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said. So doesn't
that sound like he damaged the מתנות matnos of here it's not
מתנות כהונה matnos kehuna but we're making an analogy, gifts to the
poor and gifts to the כהנים. Kohanim. So because he took it
and he really wasn't fully entitled to it, he now has to
pay back. So of course it's a little funny because how would
we have allowed him to do it if he really was considered
like he was damaging or stealing or whatever? So it's a funny
question, but the גמרא Gemara here thinks it's an analogy. It's like
he took something he wasn't entitled to although we did let him
do it and therefore he has to pay back. So don't you
see that you that you do have to pay back? So אמר
רב חסדא amar Rav Chisda מדת חסידות שנו כאן. middas chasidus shanu
kan. Yeah, he doesn't really have to, we're not going to collect
it in court. If he wants to be a good guy, he'll
pay back for what he took. So אמר רבא amar Rava so
רבא Rava said תני תנא ישלם ואת אמרת מדת חסידות שנו כאן?
tani tanna yeshalem ve'at amart middas chasidus shanu kan? רבא Rava says
that can't have been how this discussion went down. First of all,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says pay. When we're not going to say
pay means do it if you're a nice guy. Pay means you're
obligated to pay. Number one. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda could not
have made his comment in reference to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. ועוד
מדירבי אליעזר ליכא למשמע מינה ve'od mideRabbi Eliezer leika lemishma mina what
type of a question is it from רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? He's
a single opinion. That wouldn't have challenged our idea. Fine, that's רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's opinion. We're not bound by רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
אלא רבא *Ella Rava* says you misunderstood the question and you misunderstood
the answer. Here was the question. מסיפא *Mi'seifa*, the end of that
משנה *Mishnah*. וחכמים אומרים *Ve'Chachamim omrim*, the sages say by this rich
person who has no money and is traveling, עני היה באותה שעה
*ani haya be'oto sha*, that he was poor at that moment, at
that moment he had no funds, so he's entitled to collect these
gifts to the poor and he doesn't have to pay back. That's
what the חכמים *Chachamim* say. Okay, how's that relevant for us? For
the following way. טעמא דעני *Ta'ama de'ani*, the reason he doesn't have
to pay back is because he really was in that context poor.
העשיר *Ha'ashir*, let's say he had been rich. Let's say I just,
I have money and I go and I take לקט שכחה פאה
*leket shikcha pe'ah*, and I go and I take מעשר עני *ma'aser
ani*. The implication is is that if you can't say that at
that moment I'm poor and I took it, I would have to
pay back, right? העשיר משלם *Ha'ashir meshalem*, I would have to pay
back. אמאי *Amai*, why would I have to pay back if I
took לקט שכחה פאה *leket shikcha pe'ah* even if I had money?
להוי כמזיק מתנות כהונה או שאכלן *Lehavi kemazik matnot kehuna o she'achalan*,
let it be here that I just destroyed, the same way if
I destroyed gifts of the כהנים *Kohanim* I don't have to pay
it back, here I destroyed, ate or destroyed gifts of the poor.
Why do I have to pay it back? And on this אמר
רב חסדא *amar Rav Chisda* מידת חסידות שנו כאן *midat chasidut shanu
kan*. You're right. Technically, if I went ahead with my money in
the bank and I went ahead and I went into a field
and I took the לקט שכחה פאה *leket shikcha pe'ah* and I
took the מעשר עני *ma'aser ani* and I ate it, so I
would have stolen from the עניים *aniyim*, but nobody could bring me
to court because which עני *ani* is going to bring me to
court? ממון שאין לו תובעים *mamon she'ein lo tovim*. So therefore, am
I obligated? I'm not obligated in the court sense, but in that
case I should, I should as a מידת חסידות *midat chasidut*, even
a little more than a מידת חסידות *midat chasidut*, I should make
a donation to the עני *ani*. Okay, so when I was poor
because I was traveling, then I was totally entitled, I don't have
to feel any responsibility, at that time I was entitled to take.
But if I took when I wasn't entitled to take, maybe somebody
can't bring me to court, but if I'm a good guy then
I definitely should make a similar donation back to the poor. So
we are left with maintaining our claim that if somebody damages either
the gifts of כהנים *Kohanim* before they're given over or the gifts
of עניים *aniyim*, you do not have to, you cannot be made
to pay in court, but there are two different reasons. One is
it really is owned by the class, the collective of כהנים *Kohanim*
or the collective of עניים *aniyim*, but just nobody is able to
file suit, ממון שאין לו תובעים *mamon she'ein lo tovim*, and the
other explanation is it isn't even owned by them. It's owned by
me, so I got out of my מצוה *mitzvah*, but I did
not damage their property. Two very different explanations. To be continued.